<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://shibaji7.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://shibaji7.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-10-15T19:22:14+00:00</updated><id>https://shibaji7.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Shibaji Chakraborty -- Ph.D. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Debunking Internet Apoclypse!</title><link href="https://shibaji7.github.io/blog/2024/internet-apoclypse/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Debunking Internet Apoclypse!"/><published>2024-04-28T07:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-28T07:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://shibaji7.github.io/blog/2024/internet-apoclypse</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://shibaji7.github.io/blog/2024/internet-apoclypse/"><![CDATA[<blockquote> If I had written this article before 2020; the word ‘Apocalypse’ would have taken me to my childhood days. Just like any other Indian millennial kid, my toddler and teenage days were full of stories. My ‘audiobook’, my grandmother, used to read out stories from old Hindu scriptures. Many of them are depictions of apocalyptical days. I heard it in my native language, Bengali! However, the 2020–2021 ‘Black Swan’ days completely reshaped my associative memory about the word ‘Apocalypse’. </blockquote> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset=" /assets/img/SS-IA-480.webp 480w, /assets/img/SS-IA-800.webp 800w, /assets/img/SS-IA-1400.webp 1400w, " sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/SS-IA.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Submarine Cables" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> ‘End of the Internet’ — is that correct? Credit: FOX Weather News </div> <h3 id="know-the-source-of-the-term-internet-apoclypse">Know the source of the term ‘Internet Apoclypse’</h3> <p>Being a Space Weather researcher I came across this scientific paper ‘<a href="https://ics.uci.edu/~sabdujyo/papers/sigcomm21-cme.pdf">Solar Superstorms: Planning for an Internet Apocalypse</a>’ written by <a href="https://ics.uci.edu/~sabdujyo/">Dr. Jyothi</a>, a few years back while working with one of the renowned scientists in the field of space weather <a href="https://i.cbc.ca/1.3569967.1462549552!/fileImage/httpImage/david-boteler.jpg">Dr. Boteler</a>. Dr. Jyothi is an Assistant Professor at the Department of Computer Science at UCLA, Irvine. The scientific paper describes the impact of ‘Solar Superstorms’ on the global internet infrastructure.</p> <blockquote> <p>A Short Note on ‘Solar Superstorms’: There is a special category of solar storms, leading to large Coronal Mass Ejections (CMEs), which then induce larger than expected ‘magnetic storm’ at near-Earth or ‘Geospace’ environment. Scientist at NOAA and NASA call them ‘Solar Superstorms’. These Solar Superstorms are typically rare events which can create very high monetary damage and impact on the geospace and modern civilization by damaging space craft, impacting health of the astronauts, and even impacting long electrical wires on the surface of the Earth.</p> </blockquote> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset=" /assets/img/Storm-480.webp 480w, /assets/img/Storm-800.webp 800w, /assets/img/Storm-1400.webp 1400w, " sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/Storm.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Solar Storms" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> An artistic rendering of the solar surface during 'Solar Superstorm’. Image Credit: NASA. </div> <blockquote> <p>Are we going to suffocate to death by not being able to visit Instagram or not being able to post to X (formally Twitter)?</p> <p>Well it depends on your compulsion level about your media activity and phone addiction levels, hence can imagine the answer to this question is subjective.</p> </blockquote> <p>Enough of these nerdy jokes, let’s come to the facts. The term ‘Internet Apocalypse’ was picked up by various media and projected as an ‘End-of-Day’ scenario and used as a click-bait to gain profit. I’ve listed a few articles below for your reference. This is not a personal rant against any media house but rather a holistic try to outlaying the information front of the general audience that I have the luxury of being a professional in the field. I guess, it is in our human psyche to discuss and fantasize about these extreme events. Besides, I have no personal grudge against any media house until they are reporting it correctly.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset=" /assets/img/induction-480.webp 480w, /assets/img/induction-800.webp 800w, /assets/img/induction-1400.webp 1400w, " sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/induction.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Power lines" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Image illustrating how space weather induce electric currents in long conductors such as power lines, pipelines, and submarine network causing power system outages or pipeline corrosion. Credit: NRCan. </div> <blockquote> <p>But the question remains:</p> <ul> <li>Is it going to happen? If ‘yes’, what do Jyothi et al. have to say about it?</li> <li>Are there any mitigation or disaster management plans?</li> </ul> </blockquote> <p>Let’s start from the top, Jyothi et al. mentioned the ‘Solar Superstorm’ as a Black-swan event for internet infrastructure. The long-distance internet cables, on land and under the water, that connect multiple large-data servers (eventually they are the internet, OR web2.0) are severely disrupted due to these ‘Solar Superstorms’ — induced ‘magnetic storms’. These magnetic storms created by big magnetic vortices near the Earth disrupted by the solar storm, as per the image below. The induced large magnetic vortices induce ground electric fields (referred to as geoelectric fields [GEF]), which creates ground induced currents (referred to as geomagnetically induced currents [GIC]) flowing through long-distance conductors, such as internet cables. Now, the study Jyothi et al mentioned, GICs can lead to long term irreparable damages to land-based or under water long-distance internet cables — Is that true? Short answer is ‘NO’. The explanation need a separate paragraph.</p> <h3 id="how-a-solar-storm-disrupts-web20">How a Solar storm disrupts web2.0?</h3> <p>Michael Faraday proved moving bar-magnet induce an electric current to a nearby electrical wire. This principle is also used by turbine-dynamo in power plants to create electrical power. It’s a remarkably profound idea scientifically referred to as ‘electromagnetic induction’. These solar magnetic storms can change magnetic fields around the Earth that are hundreds of thousands of kilometers long, leading to a strong induction on long distance conducting wires around us, some of them are tens and hundreds of kilometers across. One example of this conducting wire is Internet cables.</p> <blockquote> <p>Don’t lose your sleep over an ‘Internet Apocalypse’</p> </blockquote> <p>While there are a large number of media reports on this topic, there is no need to lose your sleep over it. With modern technological advancement more than 95% of internet traffic is routed via submarine internet cables (cables under the water). So, we have a huge reliance on them. The new age internet cables are fiber-optics by nature that are immune to GICs. The underwater internet cables are shielded by the water itself from the induction effects, commonly known as ‘electromagnetic shielding’ — probably a separate topic. In a single word, this shielding mechanism reduced the strength of the induction process and associated impact on the underwater cables.</p> <blockquote> <p>What Specialists are saying?</p> </blockquote> <p>Having said all this, there are recorded history of submarine cable voltages getting impacted by magnetic storms. On February 10, 1958 solar storm created alternately loud squawks and faint whispers on the transatlantic communication between Clarenville, Newfoundland, to Oban, Scotland. The naturally induced voltage created constructive and destructive interference with the cable supply voltage.</p> <p>As I mentioned new age cables are more robust and made of optical fibers. However, there is still a conductor through the cable to carry the power to the repeaters. During the March 1989 storm, a new transatlantic (deployed at that time, known as TAT-8 cable) did not experience any disruption. However large induced voltages were observed on the power supply cables, as recorded by the operators. Current cables will use a much more robust system, fewer repeaters, and require a much higher driving voltage as dynamic range to offset any unwanted voltage and current fluctuations. I’m currently working on a project that is testing the vulnerabilities of the current cable and assessing the risk of magnetic storms on them. I’ll update a separate blog as I progress through that.</p> <blockquote> <p>What do you have to worry about?</p> </blockquote> <p>Despite what some headlines have been saying, there’s no internet apocalypse on the horizon. However, that does not mean that 95% of internet traffic carrying submarine cables is not prone to any natural disaster. There are studies have shown that Tsunamis and underwater landslides pose a much bigger threat to submarine cables. Even ship anchors are a much bigger concern for a few cables than Solar Superstorms — Not a Joke! While these natural calamities may pose a threat to global connectivity, rest assured it is not going to wipe out the global connection in a single shot.</p> <p>However, if any natural calamity is causing some scenario like ‘Internet Apocalypse’ then I would rather worry more about my life over my tweeter feed — Again not a Joke! I’m clear about my priorities.</p> <h3 id="list-of-a-few-articles-on-internet-apoclypse">List of a few articles on ‘Internet Apoclypse’</h3> <p><a href="https://economictimes.indiatimes.com/news/international/us/internet-apocalypse-what-is-a-solar-storm-and-how-can-it-impact-the-internet-on-earth/articleshow/101287452.cms?from=mdr" title=""><img src="https://img.etimg.com/thumb/msid-101287483,width-300,height-225,imgsize-67680,resizemode-75/internet-apocalypse-what-is-a-solar-storm-and-how-can-it-impact-the-internet-on-earth.jpg" width="100%" style="max-width: 850px;" alt=""/></a><br/>Provided by Economics Times<a href="" target="_blank"></a></p> <p><a href="https://www.outlookindia.com/international/internet-apocalypse-solar-storm-2025-nasa-communication-news-302259" title=""><img src="https://media.assettype.com/outlookindia/import/public/uploads/articles/2017/12/15/solar_system_630_630.jpg?w=640&amp;auto=format%2Ccompress&amp;fit=max&amp;format=webp&amp;dpr=1.0" width="100%" style="max-width: 850px;" alt=""/></a><br/>Provided by Outlook India<a href="" target="_blank"></a></p>]]></content><author><name>Shibaji Chakraborty</name></author><category term="sample-posts"/><category term="GMD"/><category term="magnetic-induction"/><category term="CME"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The question is not 'If' but 'When'!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Solar Burps</title><link href="https://shibaji7.github.io/blog/2024/solar-burps/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Solar Burps"/><published>2024-04-16T07:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-16T07:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://shibaji7.github.io/blog/2024/solar-burps</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://shibaji7.github.io/blog/2024/solar-burps/"><![CDATA[<blockquote> It was the last week of August 2017, the start of Fall semester; I was rushing in my bike towards Hutcheson Hall, Virginia Tech, to attend my graduate-level probability class. I received an email alert on my phone from NOAA stating there was a strong chance in Solar Storm that might impact Earth by next week. Being a noob in the field at that time (although I do not consider myself a connoisseur yet…) it felt incredibly impossible to observe a scenario like that during the last solar cycle (defined by the solar magnetic phases). Eventually, they were right about the prediction, and there was the biggest solar storm of that solar cycle that hits the Earth. NASA calls these solar storms Solar Burps. </blockquote> <p>The Sun, in the visible spectrum, light that the human eye is sensitive to, looks remarkably consistent. It nonchalantly powers our solar system with its light and heat without any expectation from us or any other planet of the solar system, for that matter. So, how come a Sun-like quiescent star can create a storm and we can never see that coming? One can unveil the truth if he/she observes the Sun in the X-ray spectrum. To be specific, the Sun in the X-ray spectrum is the most hostile place for life in our solar system that Burps every now and then and creates a problem for us.</p> <blockquote> <p>Don’t worry the Sun has no digestive system, it does not eat humans, and has no digestive issues!</p> </blockquote> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset=" /assets/img/Storm-480.webp 480w, /assets/img/Storm-800.webp 800w, /assets/img/Storm-1400.webp 1400w, " sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/Storm.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Monitoring" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> A depiction of a coronal mass ejection, with Earth to scale. Image credits: NASA / Goddard. </div> <p>I wanted to debunk a few less-known facts:</p> <ul> <li>Should we worry about the solar storms that are heading towards us?</li> <li>Should we hunker down inside and disconnect our Kitchen appliances, TV, phone, and internet?</li> <li>OR, is this just hype about a non-event made by the media?</li> </ul> <p>Just like most of the other things in life, the reality is somewhere between ‘yes’ and ‘no’. The subjective nature comes from the shape and structure of these storms. Solar storms can create very real damage to electrical equipment. A solar storm on March 1989, one of the strongest solar storm in recent recorded history, caused several nights of darkness over Quebec and Canada. That’s not it, approximately, five years later two of the Anik communication satellites were taken out of commission, one for hours, another for months, due to a solar storm. Moreover, these storms can destroy satellites by deorbiting them from their trajectories. For example, a 2022 solar storm resulted in the Starlink transmitters drifting back into Earth’s atmosphere, where they will burn up, potentially costing the company about $100 million. The extraordinary solar storm that occurred in 1859 is the strongest solar storm of recorded human history, also known as the ‘Carrington Event’.</p> <blockquote> <p>But how do solar storms create havoc in electrical equipment and satellites and spare us? What are these solar storms actually anyway?</p> </blockquote> <p>Let’s start targeting the second question first. As mentioned earlier the Sun is anything but calm, but that is in X-ray and EUV spectrum. Infect the Sun’s atmosphere is highly active. When the Sun “Burps!”, it spews stellar material and magnetic fields from the surface of the Sun towards the solar system sometimes towards the Earth. These burps are often associated with other solar events, such as X-rays, charged particles, and magnetized plasma across the solar system.</p> <p>The Sun, being the powerhouse of the solar system, releases enormous amounts of power every second, roughly ‘25 trillion’ (i.e. 25,000,000,000,000!) times that required by the inhabitants of the Earth. Let us digest the fact. What I mean is, the Sun produces \(25\times10^{12}\) times of all mankind’s needs each second! For analogy, a typical household needs ‘1000 watts’ (kilowatts) per second, while its supplier power plant generates power in ‘Million’ (mega, \(10^{6}\)) Watts. So, as per this analogy there are ‘1,000,000’ power plants with each having a capacity of ‘25 megawatts’ supplying power to only ‘one house’.</p> <p>This huge amount of power in the Sun is generated by ‘nuclear fusion’ reaction and ‘solar magnetic fields’, creating it a ‘plasma blob’ in space. These complex thermonuclear processes make the Sun’s surface bubble like a cauldron. We can see structures on scales from thousands of kilometers down to just a few (see this incredible image for an example) and probably smaller. However, some of the structures may be in the order of Earth or sometimes 100s of Earth (check the previous image on top). Additionally, we can see ‘extremely bright and dark spots’ on top of the Sun’s surface.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset=" /assets/img/Burps-structures-480.webp 480w, /assets/img/Burps-structures-800.webp 800w, /assets/img/Burps-structures-1400.webp 1400w, " sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/Burps-structures.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> A closer look at the Sun's surface, showing solar active regions and sunspots. Image credits: NASA / Goddard. </div> <p>These extremely bright and dark spots are referred to as ‘solar active regions’ and ‘Sunspots’. All these structures stem from intense magnetic field activity and plasma processes. They act like energy storage units and possess enormous amounts of energy within them. Magnetic and plasma activities deposit energy into these regions semi-periodically. Suppose regions are unable to store the energy. In that case, they release it to outer space by producing huge flares/eruptions, which send billions of tons of hot ‘plasma’ (the energetic charged particles) into space traveling at two million kilometers per hour, commonly known as ‘Coronal Mass Ejection (CME)’ or ‘Solar Burps’.</p> <p>Now, let’s deal with the first question: Why the solar storms spare us, humans, or any other living organisms, and impact the electrical equipment. The answer to this question is two-fold. First, unlike tropical storms (which stem from atmospheric temperature or pressure difference), solar storms are ‘magnetic storms’. What do I mean by that? In short, these storms stem from electric and magnetic potential differences. I will discuss that in detail in a separate post.</p> <blockquote> <p>Why ‘magnetic storm’ is a problem for electrical equipment?</p> </blockquote> <p>Well, over 200 years ago ‘Michael Faraday’ demonstrated that if you hold a bar magnet and move it rapidly near a wire, it will produce an electric current through the wire. It is the same principle that is used by turbine-dynamo in power plants to create electrical power. It’s a straightforward but remarkably profound idea, scientists called it electromagnetic induction. These solar magnetic storms can change magnetic fields around the Earth that are hundreds of thousands of kilometers long, leading to a strong induction on the surface of the Earth. Now the wires around us, some of them are tens and hundreds of kilometers across (e.g., high voltage transmission lines carrying power from power grids to local distribution stations or our houses), start getting some serious induced electrical currents. One example was, the March 1989 storm, that caused enough electrical surge to shut down the Quebec power grid. Hence, the electrical equipments and power grids are prone to large-scale magnetic storms, unlike humans.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset=" /assets/img/Sun-Earth-480.webp 480w, /assets/img/Sun-Earth-800.webp 800w, /assets/img/Sun-Earth-1400.webp 1400w, " sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/Sun-Earth.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> A depiction of the Sun-Earth system. The image illustrates how Earth's magnetic fields get distorted by CME and divert millions of tons of plasma. Image credits: NASA / Goddard. </div> <p>While we are not susceptible to magnetic induction, ‘high-energy plasma’ can cause severe damage to any living organism. But the good news is magnetic fields and the atmosphere around the Earth protect us from the worst of these high-energy particles and solar radiation.</p> <blockquote> <p>Are we often right in the firing line?</p> </blockquote> <p>The short answer to this question is ‘yes’. While billions of tons of plasma (and X-rays) are traveling at ‘relativistic speed’ (a speed that reaches the speed of light) like it would wipe out everything in its path, by the time it reaches the Earth it’s spread out over a vast area. This space near the Earth, where there is no atmosphere, or we are protected by Earth’s magnetic field is called near-Earth space or ‘Geo-space’. The density of plasma is so low here that if you could imagine standing up in the wind of particles traveling at millions of kilometers an hour, you wouldn’t feel a thing, but your body cells will. While one short dose of these high-energy plasma particles might not kill you, but a prolonged and constant bombardment of DNA leads to cancer. That’s one of the reasons why sending astronauts to Mars is so tough. But don’t worry if you are not traveling to Mars soon, and I guess Elon is building some protective shielding for us in his space shuttle to Mars (a topic for a separate story!).</p> <p>Imagination aside, these have a severe impact on our modern civilization. Losing satellites and power grids can cost billions of dollars. Most of them can cause irreplaceable damage, not to mention public safety issues. So, it should come as no surprise that predicting these events and building safety measures for both satellites and power distribution systems is one of the primary goals of national security. Early warning systems are well in place now - we get anywhere between two-to-five days’ notice. Check NOAA websites if you want to get more details on this.</p> <blockquote> <p>Can we observe a remanence of a ‘magnetic storm’?</p> </blockquote> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset=" /assets/img/Aurora-480.webp 480w, /assets/img/Aurora-800.webp 800w, /assets/img/Aurora-1400.webp 1400w, " sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/Aurora.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> A green aurora, somewhere in the Alask, USA. Image credits: University Alaska at Fairbanks. </div> <p>Every storm comes with a ‘Rainbow’. Just like any tropical storm, a magnetic storm creates its own Rainbow (kind of); we refer to it as ‘Aurora’. It is an out-of-the-world scene one can experience. Earth’s magnetic fields divert the energetic plasma particles, trap a part of those energetic particles and stream them around the Earth’s magnetic pole causing Aurora. More about Aurora and their formation mechanism in a later post…</p> <p>In summary, we have not seen a truly large solar storm and associated magnetic storm in over 100 years. Neither of these two events in March 1989 or September 2017 compares to the great solar storm of 1859 (‘Carrington Event’), which is known to be the largest known ‘solar storm’. With the insurgence of modern numerical techniques and AI tools, we think we have the capability of predicting the scale of a large solar storm. The reality might be much grave than what we expect, the reason of our reliance of electrical equipment and satellites increasing day-by-day, and we are unaware of the fact how much a large solar storm may cost us!</p> <blockquote> While Sun may give us life, one extra big 'Burp' could produce some grave problems. I would like to 'think' myself as a non-believer but may be this is the reason ancient civilizations treated the Sun as a God! </blockquote>]]></content><author><name>Shibaji Chakraborty</name></author><category term="sample-posts"/><category term="CME"/><category term="GMD"/><category term="Flare"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In reality it's anything but calm!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Eclipse Glasses</title><link href="https://shibaji7.github.io/blog/2024/eclipse-glass/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Eclipse Glasses"/><published>2024-04-11T07:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-11T07:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://shibaji7.github.io/blog/2024/eclipse-glass</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://shibaji7.github.io/blog/2024/eclipse-glass/"><![CDATA[<p>Solar eclipse glasses have been created for the sole purpose of protecting your retinas should you be lucky enough to experience a solar eclipse. Solar eclipse glasses are specially designed with a so-called solar filter, an elaborate piece of technology that is engineered to block, among others, the ‘harmful wavelength’ of sun radiation. This solar filter blocks light from outside the visible spectrum (polychromatic ultraviolet or UV and polychromatic infrared or IR radiation) perfectly fine, as well as all intense visible light that might escape quantitative absorbance.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset=" /assets/img/eclipse-glass-iop-480.webp 480w, /assets/img/eclipse-glass-iop-800.webp 800w, /assets/img/eclipse-glass-iop-1400.webp 1400w, " sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/eclipse-glass-iop.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Eclipse Glasses" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Photo by Jason Howell on Unsplash; Typical eclipse glasses distributed by NASA. </div> <h3 id="what-are-they-made-of">What are they made of?</h3> <p>These glasses are constructed differently from regular sunglasses or tinted glasses. While normal sunglasses usually allow between 10 and 20 percent of daylight (specifically, visible spectrum) to pass through their glasses, the sunlight transmitted can still be too bright for safe viewing of the sun. I’ll write a separate post about ‘‘Understanding How Regular Sunglasses Reduce Visible Light Intensity’’.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset=" /assets/img/eclipse-glasses-480.webp 480w, /assets/img/eclipse-glasses-800.webp 800w, /assets/img/eclipse-glasses-1400.webp 1400w, " sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/eclipse-glasses.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Monitoring" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Me trying to see the 2017 Great American Eclipse with RayBan. Photo Credit: Alamy.com. </div> <blockquote> <p>Rick Fienberg, the press officer for the American Astronomical Society (AAS), explained to <a href="https://www.space.com/36941-solar-eclipse-eye-protection-guide.html">Space.com</a> that the filters specifically designed for viewing the sun are significantly darker, allowing only a minuscule fraction of light to pass through. In fact, these specialized solar filters are typically around 100,000 times (five order of magnitude) darker than regular sunglasses. He also noted that the majority of ISO-approved eclipse glasses rely on solar filters produced by <a href="https://astrosolar.com/en/products/whitelight/solar-viewer-astrosolar-silver-gold/">AstroSolar</a> and <a href="https://thousandoaksoptical.com/shop/eclipse/solar-viewer-cards-glasses/">Thousand Oaks Optical</a>.</p> </blockquote> <p>Typically, eclipse glasses are made of a thin metallic film with high optical density. Optical density of film material is an important parameter that ensures the lenses are capable of providing adequate protection against the bright solar corona during the eclipse. A high optical density indicates better protection against UV and IR radiation, and visible light. Hence, these materials make it safer for viewing solar disk during events like eclipses. For example, AstroSolar consists of Baader AstroSolar Silver/Gold Film, which provides eye-sided reflex-free viewing. Additionally, gold blocks infrared (IR) radiation, ensuring there is no unpleasant feeling of warmth in the eyeball. The optical density (OD) of these glasses is OD=5.0, indicating their high level of protection.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset=" /assets/img/OD-480.webp 480w, /assets/img/OD-800.webp 800w, /assets/img/OD-1400.webp 1400w, " sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/OD.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Monitoring" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Illustration of optical density (OD). Image Credit: [Dr.-Ing. Oliver Pust]. Check his X-post for details. </div> <h3 id="a-short-note-of-on-optical-density-od">A short note of on optical density (OD).</h3> <p>OD quantifies a material’s ability to attenuate the intensity of light passing through it. A material with higher OD can absorb light significantly in comparison to a material with lower OD. For example, a material with an OD=2.0 reduces the intensity of light by a factor of 100 in comparison to a material with OD=0.</p> <h3 id="is-there-any-alternative-to-these-metallic-film-glasses">Is there any alternative to these metallic film glasses?</h3> <p>Yes, there are alternatives to metallic film eclipse glasses. People use the following items e.g., ‘Welder’s Goggles’, ‘Pinhole Camera’, and ‘X-ray films’. X-ray films are most cheapest and creative way to see eclipse/sun. A tweet from the Bureau of Land Management in Arizona suggested a ‘creative way to view the eclipse,’ with the photo of an employee using what appears to be an X-ray to look up at the sun.</p> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">The BLM Arizona State Office found a creative way to view the eclipse; thru xrays <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Eclipse2017?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#Eclipse2017</a> <a href="https://t.co/MR5UNbyuPH">pic.twitter.com/MR5UNbyuPH</a></p>&mdash; Bureau of Land Management - Arizona (@BLMArizona) <a href="https://twitter.com/BLMArizona/status/899720621726105600?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">August 21, 2017</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>]]></content><author><name>Shibaji Chakraborty</name></author><category term="sample-posts"/><category term="space"/><category term="eclipse"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How do eclipse glasses work?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">About Me</title><link href="https://shibaji7.github.io/blog/2024/about-me/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="About Me"/><published>2024-04-09T07:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-09T07:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://shibaji7.github.io/blog/2024/about-me</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://shibaji7.github.io/blog/2024/about-me/"><![CDATA[<p>I am a Space Weather researcher at <a href="https://www.space.vt.edu/">Space@VT</a>, <a href="https://www.vt.edu/">Virginia Tech</a>. As a Space Weather researcher, I specialize in exploring the effects and impacts of Space Weather on our modern civilization in near-Earth space. My journey in this field has been shaped by years of experience and a deep passion for unraveling the mysteries of our cosmic environment.</p> <p>Over the years, I have contributed extensively to various scientific journals and publications, delving into complex topics and addressing expert audiences. While this has been fulfilling, I have recently felt a calling to broaden my reach and make science more accessible to the general public.</p> <p>I believe that science should not be confined to academic circles but should be made understandable and relevant to everyone. With this goal in mind, I am embarking on a journey to bridge the gap between scientific research and public understanding. Through engaging and informative mediums like Medium articles, I aim to demystify Space Weather concepts and share the wonders of our universe with a wider audience. Venturing into the world of Medium is an exciting step for me, not only to share my ideas but also to expand my writing horizons and connect with a broader audience.</p> <p>By engaging with experienced writers and absorbing their insights, I aim to refine my craft and develop a unique voice that resonates with readers. I’m excited to immerse myself in the vibrant community of Medium, where ideas flourish, and creativity knows no bounds. With each article published, I anticipate gaining valuable feedback and honing my skills as a writer.</p> <p>But this journey isn’t just about my own growth; it’s about fostering a sense of curiosity and wonder in others. Through thought-provoking content and meaningful interactions, I hope to inspire curiosity, spark conversations, and ignite a passion for learning in my readers.</p> <p>Join me on this exciting adventure as we explore the mysteries of Space Weather together and empower individuals to better understand and appreciate the dynamic forces shaping our cosmic neighborhood.</p>]]></content><author><name>Shibaji Chakraborty</name></author><category term="sample-posts"/><category term="space"/><category term="science"/><category term="me"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A tale of me - Shibaji Chakraborty!]]></summary></entry></feed>