<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://shibaji7.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://shibaji7.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-04-16T22:07:01+00:00</updated><id>https://shibaji7.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Shibaji Chakraborty -- Ph.D. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Internet Apoclypse!</title><link href="https://shibaji7.github.io/blog/2024/internet-apoclypse/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Internet Apoclypse!"/><published>2024-04-16T16:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-16T16:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://shibaji7.github.io/blog/2024/internet-apoclypse</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://shibaji7.github.io/blog/2024/internet-apoclypse/"><![CDATA[<blockquote> Just like any other Indian millenial kid, my toddler and teanage days were full of stories . My 'audio book', my grandmother, Annapurna Chakraborty, she used to read out stories from old </blockquote>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sample-posts"/><category term="GMD"/><category term="magnetic-induction"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The question is not 'If' but 'When'!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Solar Burps</title><link href="https://shibaji7.github.io/blog/2024/solar-burps/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Solar Burps"/><published>2024-04-16T07:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-16T07:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://shibaji7.github.io/blog/2024/solar-burps</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://shibaji7.github.io/blog/2024/solar-burps/"><![CDATA[<blockquote> It was the last week of August 2017, the start of Fall semester, I was rushing in my bike towards Hutcheson Hall, Virginia Tech, to attend my graduate-level probability class. I received an email alert in my phone from NOAA stating there was a strong chance in Solar Storm that might impact Earth by next week. Being a noob in the field at that time (although I do not consider myself a connoisseur yet…) it felt incredibly impossible to observe a scenario like that during a declining phase of the last solar cycle. Eventually, they were right about the prediction and there was the biggest solar storm of that solar cycle that hits the Earth. NASA calls these solar storms Solar Burps. </blockquote> <p>The Sun in visible spectrum, light that that human eye is sensitive to, looks remarkably consistent, nonchalantly powering our solar system by its light and heat without any expectation from us or any other planet of the solar system for that matter.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset=" /assets/img/Storm-480.webp 480w, /assets/img/Storm-800.webp 800w, /assets/img/Storm-1400.webp 1400w, " sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/Storm.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Monitoring" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> A depiction of a coronal mass ejection, with Earth to scale. Image credits: NASA / Goddard. </div> <p>Now the major questions are:</p> <ul> <li>Should we worry about the solar storms that are heading towards us? Should we hunker down inside and disconnect our Kitchen appliances, TV, phone, and internet?</li> <li>OR, is this just hype about a non-event made by media?</li> </ul> <p>Just like most of the other things in life, the reality is somewhere between ‘yes’ and ‘no’. The subjective nature comes from the morphology of these storms. Solar storms can create very real damage to electrical equipment. March 1989 storm created a few dark nights over Quebec, Canada by causing severe damages to power feed lines. Approximately, five years later two of the Anik communication satellites were taken out of commission, one for hours, another for months, due to a solar storm. These storms can destroy satellites by deorbiting them from their trajectories. For example, a 2022 solar storm resulted in the Starlink transmitters drifting back into Earth’s atmosphere, where they will burn up, potentially costing the company about $100 million.</p> <blockquote> <p>But how do solar storms create havoc in electrical equipment and satellites and spare us? What are these solar storms actually anyway?</p> </blockquote> <p>Let’s start targeting the second question first. As mentioned earlier the Sun is anything but calm, but that is in X-ray and EUV spectrum. Infect the Sun’s atmosphere is highly active. When the Sun “Burps!”, it spews stellar material and magnetic fields from the surface of the sun towards the solar system- some time towards the Earth. These burps are often associated with other solar events, such as X-rays, charged particles, and magnetized plasma across the solar system.</p> <p>The Sun, being the powerhouse of the solar system, releases enormous amounts of power <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">every second</code>, roughly <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">25 trillion</code> (i.e. 25,000,000,000,000!) times that required by the inhabitants of the Earth. Let us digest the fact, first, it is \(25\times 10^12\) times of all mankind’s need! For analogy, a typical household needs <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">1000 watts</code> (kilo watts) per second, while its supplier power plant generates power in <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Million (Mega) Watts</code> \(10^6\). So, as per this analogy there are <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">1,000,000</code> power plants with each having capacity of <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">25 megawatts</code> supplying power to one <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">House</code>.</p> <p>This huge amount of power in the Sun is generated by <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">nuclear fusion</code> reaction and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">solar magnetic fields</code>, creating it a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">plasma blob</code> in space. These complex processes make the Sun’s surface bubble like a cauldron. We can see structure on scales from thousands of kilometers down to just a few (see this incredible image for an example) and probably smaller. However, some of the structures may be in the order of Earth or sometimes 100s of Earth (check previous image on top). Additionally, we can see <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">extremely bright and dark spots</code> on top of the Sun’s surface.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset=" /assets/img/Burps-structures-480.webp 480w, /assets/img/Burps-structures-800.webp 800w, /assets/img/Burps-structures-1400.webp 1400w, " sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/Burps-structures.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> A closer look at the Sun's surface, showing solar active regions and sunspots. Image credits: NASA / Goddard. </div> <p>These extremely bright and dark spots are referred to as <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">solar active regions</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Sunspots</code>. All these structures stem from <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">intense magnetic field activity</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">plasma processes</code>. They possess enormous amounts of stored energy within them and act like storage units with an associated storage limit. Magnetic and plasma activities deposits energy into these regions continuously or semi-periodically. If regions are unable to store the energy, then they release it to outer space by producing huge flares/eruptions which send billions of tons of hot <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">plasma</code> (energetic particles) into space travelling at two million kilometers per hour, commonly known as <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Coronal Mass Ejection (CME)</code> or <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Solar Burps</code>.</p> <p>NNow, let’s deal with the second question on why these solar storms spare us, humans, or any other living organisms, and impact the electrical equipment. Answer to this question is two-fold. First, unlike tropical storms (stem from atmospheric temperature or pressure difference) solar storms are <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">magnetic storms</code>. What do I mean by that? In short, these storms stem from electric and magnetic potential differences. I will discuss that in detail in a separate post.</p> <blockquote> <p>Why <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">magnetic storm</code> is a problem for electrical equipments?</p> </blockquote> <p>Well, over 200 years ago <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Michael Faraday</code> demonstrated that if you hold a bar-magnet and move it rapidly near a wire, it will produce an electric current through the wire. It is the same principle that is used by <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">turbine-dynamo</code> in power plants to create electrical power. It’s a really simple but incredibly profound idea, scientists called it <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">electromagnetic induction</code>. These solar <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">magnetic storms</code> can change magnetic fields around the Earth that are hundreds of thousands of kilometers long, leading to a strong induction on the Earth surface. Now the wires around us, some of them are tens and hundreds of kilometers across, start getting some serious electrical currents induced. One example was, March 1989 storm, that caused enough electrical surge to shut down the Quebec power grid. Hence, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">electromagnetic induction</code> the electrical equipment on power grids is <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">prone</code> to large scale <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">magnetic storms</code> unlike humans.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset=" /assets/img/Sun-Earth-480.webp 480w, /assets/img/Sun-Earth-800.webp 800w, /assets/img/Sun-Earth-1400.webp 1400w, " sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/Sun-Earth.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> A depiction of the Sun-Earth system. The image illustrates how Earth's magnetic fields get distorted by CME and diverts million tons of plasma. Image credits: NASA / Goddard. </div> <p>While we are not susceptible to magnetic induction but <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">high energy plasma</code> can cause severe damage to any living organism. But the good news is magnetic fields around the Earth protect us from the worst of these high energy particles. Our atmosphere also protects us from solar radiation and energetic particles.</p> <blockquote> <p>Are we often right in the firing line?</p> </blockquote> <p>The short answer to this question is <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">yes</code>. While billions of tons of plasma (and X-rays) are travelling at <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">relativistic speed</code> (a speed that reaches the speed of light) like it would wipe out everything in its path, by the time it reaches the Earth it’s spread out over a vast area. This space near the Earth, where there is no atmosphere, or we are protected by Earth’s magnetic field is called near-Earth space or <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Geo-space</code>. The density of plasma is so low here that if you could imagine standing up in the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">wind</code> of particle travelling at millions of kilometers an hour, you wouldn’t feel a thing, but your body cells will. While one short does of these high energy plasma particles might not kill you, but a prolonged and constant bombardment of DNA leads to cancer. That’s one of the reasons why sending astronauts to Mars is so tough. But don’t worry if you are not travelling to Mars. I guess Elon is building some protective shielding for us in his space shuttle to Mars.</p> <p>Imagination aside, these have severe impact on our modern civilization. Losing satellites and power grids can cost billions of dollars. Most of them can cause irreplaceable damage, not to mention public safety issues. So, it should come as no surprise that predicting these events, and building safety measures for both satellites and power distribution systems is one of the primary goals of national security. Early warning systems are well in place now – we get anywhere between two-to-five days’ notice. Check NOAA websites if you want to get more details on this.</p> <blockquote> <p>Can we observe a remanence of a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">magnetic storms</code>?</p> </blockquote> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset=" /assets/img/Aurora-480.webp 480w, /assets/img/Aurora-800.webp 800w, /assets/img/Aurora-1400.webp 1400w, " sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/Aurora.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> A green aurora, somewhere in the Alask, USA. Image credits: University Alaska at Fairbanks. </div> <p>Every storm comes with a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Rainbow</code>. Just like any tropical storm, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">magnetic storm</code> create its own <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Rainbow</code>, we refer it as <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Aurora</code>. It is an out of the world scene one can experience. Earth’s magnetic fields divert the energetic plasma particles, traps a part of those energetic particles and stream them around the Earth’s magnetic pole causing <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Aurora</code>. More about <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Aurora</code> and their formation mechanism in a later post…</p> <p>In summary, we have not seen really seen a truly large <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">solar storm</code> and associated <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">magnetic storm</code> in over 100 years. Neither of these two events in March 1989 or September 2017 compares to the great solar storm of 1859 (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Carrington Event</code>), which known to be the largest known <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">solar storm</code>. With the insurgence of modern numerical techniques and AI tool we <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">think</code> we have the capability of predicting the scale of a large <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">solar storm</code>. The reality might be much grave than what we expect, the reason of our reliance of electrical equipment and satellites increasing day-by-day, and we are unaware of the fact how much a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Carrington Event</code> may cost us!</p> <blockquote> While Sun may give us life, one extra big `Burp` could produce some grave problems. I would like to 'think' myself as a non-believer but may be this is the reason ancient civilizations treated the Sun as a God! </blockquote>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sample-posts"/><category term="CME"/><category term="GMD"/><category term="Flare"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In reality it's anything but calm!]]></summary></entry></feed>