<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://shibaji7.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://shibaji7.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-04-16T11:05:42+00:00</updated><id>https://shibaji7.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Shibaji Chakraborty -- Ph.D. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Solar Burps – In reality it’s anything but calm!</title><link href="https://shibaji7.github.io/blog/2024/solar-burps/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Solar Burps – In reality it’s anything but calm!"/><published>2024-04-16T07:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-16T07:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://shibaji7.github.io/blog/2024/solar-burps</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://shibaji7.github.io/blog/2024/solar-burps/"><![CDATA[<blockquote> <p>It was last week of August 2017, start of Fall semister, I was rushing in my bike towrads Hutcheson Hall, Virginia Tech, to attend my graduate-level probability class. I received an email alart in my phone from NOAA stating there was a strong chance in Solar Storm that might impact Earth by next week. Being a noob in the field at that time (although I do not consider myself a connisure yet…) it felt increadibly imposible to observe a senario like that during a declining phase of the last solar cycle. Eventually, they were right about the prediction and there was the biggest solar storm of that solar cycle that hits the Earth. NASA call these solar storms Solar Burps.</p> </blockquote> <p>The Sun in visible spectrum, light that that human eye is sensitive to, looks remarkably consistent, nonchalantly poweing our solar system by its light and heat without any expectation from us or any other planet of the solar system for that matter.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset=" /assets/img/Storm-480.webp 480w, /assets/img/Storm-800.webp 800w, /assets/img/Storm-1400.webp 1400w, " sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/Storm.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Monitoring" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> A depiction of a coronal mass ejection, with Earth to scale. Image credits: NASA / Goddard. </div> <p>When Sun “burps”, it spews stellar material and magnetic fields from the surface of the sun towrads the solar system- some time towrads the Earth. These burps often associated with other solar events, such as, X-rays, charged particles, and magnetized plasma across the solar system.</p> <p>Now the major questions are: Should we worry about the solar storm that is headed our? Should we hunker down inside and disconnect our TVs, toasters and breadmakers? Or is this just hype about a non-event?{: .block-tip }</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sample-posts"/><category term="CME"/><category term="GMD"/><category term="Flare"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In reality it's anything but calm!]]></summary></entry></feed>